Guide to the Libbie Ward Papers, 1828-1913 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Libbie Ward papers 1828-1913 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Ward, Libbie, 1838-1914.
1.2 Linear Feet 110 Items
Ward served with the U.S. Christian Commission in hospitals in Louisville, Ky., and Nashville, Tenn., from 1864 to 1865, where she worked in the kitchens and as a general aide to the soldiers who spent brief periods there.
Mainly letters between Libbie Ward and her family and friends.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Libbie Ward Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2001.
Biographical Note
Libbie Ward served with the U.S. Christian Commission in hospitals in Louisville, Ky., and Nashville, Tenn., from 1864 to 1865, where she worked in the kitchens and as a general aide to the soldiers who spent brief periods there. Ward was born in Massachusetts, but lived in Wisconsin most of her life. She never married.
Collection Overview
Mainly letters (106 items, 1828-1913) between Sarah Elisabeth "Libbie" Ward and her family and friends. There are letters from other hospital workers, United States Christian Commission administrators, and family members of soldiers Ward tended. The bulk of the letters date from Libbie's time working for the U.S. Christian Commission at Foundry Hospital. Topics include health and illness, religion, death, politics and the war, and family life. Ward refers to arguments with friends and co-workers about women's rights and race, and discusses her changing opinions of African-Americans due to her work with them in the South. She writes, "There are some very intelligent and fine-looking colored men here I tell you it makes one feel bad to see so many who can neither read or write, who have so unfairly been deprived of the privilege." Includes two diaries, one combined with an account book. The diary, which comprises regular entries from 21 Sept. 1864 to 1 Jan. 1865, describes her daily routines in the kitchen and on the wards at the Louisville hospital and contains her thoughts on her day-to-day struggles, often using religious language. She mentions the 1864 Battle of Franklin's aftermath several times and refers to seeing "the noted female soldier." There is an additional diary combined with an account book that includes financial details from 1865-1870, a poem, a Union election advertisement, a telegram, an essay on Intemperance, and what appears to be letter drafts. Some early letters to her father are included and letters she wrote and received in her later life (1913) to and from young relatives. (01-039).
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
United States Christian Commission
Foundry Hospital (Louisville, Ky.)
Family -- United States -- History -- 19th century
Feminism -- History -- 19th century
Women and religion -- United States -- History
Women's rights -- History -- 19th century
Tennessee -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865
Kentucky -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865
United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Medical care
United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Nurses
United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Hospitals
United States -- History -- Civil War,1861-1865 -- Personal narratives
United States -- Race relations
United States -- Social conditions
Contents of Collection
- Container List
  - Correspondence, 1864-1865 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1865-1866
  - Correspondence, 1867-1894, undated
  - Correspondence, 1844-1913, undated
  - Correspondence, 1857-1913, undated
  - Correspondence, 1828-1894
  - Miscellaneous Items, undated
  - Diary, 1864-1865
  - Transcription of Diary